Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Sandine, Robert, 2004 October 26; computer file (WAV)
    Bob Sandine discusses his move to New Haven from Minneapolis in 1960 for his and his wife's dual enrollment in the Yale Divinity School. He describes their experiences living in different New Haven neighborhoods, first in the Divinity School housing, the East Rock neighborhood and, later, Rockview Brookside, a public housing project. He details the area and neighborhood environment in Rockview Brookside, describing it as a predominately black-settled area. He talks about his family's decision to live there and discusses their relatively easy adjustment to being one of the few white families in the area. He shares anecdotes detailing the reactions of other whites against their residence in a predominately black neighborhood. He describes his community involvement as a field worker and church ministry leader. He also talks about his experiences as a high school teacher, acting coach, and school administrator. He describes his perspective of public school teachers getting involved in the Civil Rights Movement by restructuring the school curriculum and participating in teach-ins and school protests. He discusses his role in various religious and civil rights initiatives, committees, and projects encouraging religious tolerance, multi-racial dialogue, and community participation. He shares anecdotes of several groups, including Yale Religious Ministry, Ecumenical Associates, and the Black Panthers. He mentions several individuals, such as Yale Religious Ministry leader Bill Coffin, Yale Divinity School professor Charles Foreman, and Rabbi Goldberg of the Miskin Israel Synagogue.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Santarcangelo, Michael, 2004 October 13; computer file (WAV)
    Michael Santarcangelo describes his employment with Yale University since 1963. He focuses on his membership in the Yale University Union, in which his father also participated during the 1950s. He describes his interest in union organizing that started from being exposed to his parents' experiences in the union. After joining the union, he was eventually promoted to leadership positions and created strong business and personal relationships with fellow union members and leaders, such as John Wilhelm and Vinny Sirabella. He talks about why he believes that unions enhance the philosophy and practice of employer-employee relationships, sharing examples illustrating union measures in three stages: mobilization, demonstration, and negotiation. Specifically, these are: identifying the working conditions or contract terms believed to be a problem in need of change; communicating with other area and state union members to research the working conditions and contract terms of their employers; uniting members with a common interest in changing the issue and a common vision of the way in which it may be improved; forming a platform of the conditions or terms to be changed reflecting its members' concerns; creating organizing tactics against resistant labor administrators and other non-union affiliating employees; and, finally, presenting their grievances to labor authorities to negotiate and, in certain cases, change, the employees' working conditions or contract terms. Santarcangelo stresses the importance of mutual respect and tolerance in the employer-employee and labor authority-union relationships and in the general working environment.
    Interviewer: Levendis, Marissa
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Schenck, Anne, 2004 March 26; computer file (WAV)
    Anne Schenck grew up in the New York area. She later moved to New Haven with her late husband, Charles, a Yale graduate, Korean war lieutenant veteran, Pentagon correspondent, prominent estates and wills lawyer, and active civic leader. She talks about their New Haven years, discussing the changes she's noticed in the city, including the Audobon Arts District. She details her husband's leadership in a variety of local and national boards, political agencies, and non-profit organizations focused on improving New Haven. She specifically mentions his volunteer positions in the United Way, the Red Cross, and the Arts Council, and his civic leadership positions as Chairman of the New Haven Housing Authority and the Board of Education. She describes her husband's ability to organize agendas, settle disputes, and unite people in a variety of settings and situations. She reflects upon their closeness over the years despite their many community service activities and responsibilities.
    Interviewer: Marten, Carol
    Length (min): 42
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Schiavone, Joel, 2004 November 23; computer file (WAV)
    Joel Schiavone, born in New York, is a New Haven developer. He discusses his efforts to develop downtown New Haven since the 1970s. He talks about the challenges of integrating multiple areas and ideas in a development project, encompassing architecture, finances, business, and psychology. He describes why and how he got involved in developing downtown New Haven. He mentions urban renewal in the 1950s and 60s as a motivation, which, he describes, weakened downtown New Haven districts and neighborhoods. He talks about why he believes downtown areas are important to urban growth and reputation. He describes the renovation and expansion of New Haven downtown districts and neighborhoods in the context of Yale University and gives his opinion of their interplay over the years. He lists past projects to revitalize New Haven and analyzes his perceptions of their strengths and weaknesses, specifically mentioning Chapel Street's development. He compares New Haven's downtown development to that of other urban cities and college towns, such as New York City, Boston, Oxford, and Austin. He shares his vision for downtown New Haven's future, defined, he says, in for-profit sectors and the integration of downtown sites and residential neighborhoods.
    Interviewer: Kutner, Jeremy
    Length (min): 80, 30
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Schiavone, Joel, 2005 March 8; computer file (WAV)
    Joel Schivaone, born in New York, is a New Haven developer. He describes his work on various downtown projects since the 1970s and his impressions of what makes downtown areas functional, safe, and exciting. He talks about the change he's noticed over the years in New Haven's downtown arts and shopping districts, comparing them to those in other urban cities. In particular, he describes the architectural visions, strengths, and problems of the construction, maintenance, and marketing of the New Haven Coliseum. He discusses New Haven's developing downtown districts, such as Long Wharf, the Arts District, Chapel Street and Dwight Street. He weighs the roles of for-profit and non-profit corporations and activities on urban development, describing his take on the importance of a strong financial relationship between facilities and their corporate sponsors. He discusses the role of a Coliseum arena in the development of a downtown district. He compares New Haven's now-demolished Coliseum with those in both small urban cities, such as Hartford, and larger metropolises, such as New York City and San Francisco. He discusses past and present projects to revitalize New Haven neighborhoods and districts and gives his interpretation of their strengths and weaknesses.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Schirrer, Peggy, 2005 July 25; computer file (WAV)
    Peggy Schirrer was born in 1936 in Canton Illinois, graduated from Denison University and moved to New Haven in 1958 to marry her fiancé, a Yale medical student. Schirrer became involved with many women's groups at Yale University and volunteer activities in the New Haven community, but it was her participation in the Junior League that occupied most of her time. Schirrer talks about her life growing up in Illinois, being a child during World War II, and attending Denison on scholarships and loans. She cam to New Haven during Richard Lee's mayoral administration and touches on redevelopment issues in the interview. After moving to New Haven, she became a high school teacher in Woodbridge but resigned in the mid-1960s to raise her children and work in community groups. She joind the Junior League at this time and worked with the New Haven historical society and other volunteer programs. After fifteen years out of the workplace, Schirrer took a job with Xerox Learning Systems but then began to work for the national Junior League and became Director of Field Services. As a leader in the group in the 1980s, Schirrer challenged its traditionall discriminatory policies and attempted to make the League's membership more diverse by getting Jewish and African American women involved. She became interested in issues of civil rights and fair employment and attended the University of Connecticut Law School. She graduated in 1993 and worked with the League and with women in the New Haven community. She discusses the League's commitment to service and her own interest in civic involvement and issues of gender and racial discrimination.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Shanklin, Sheila, 2007 April 17; computer file (WAV)
    Sheila Shanklin recalls the beginnings of the Dwight area Management Team. The Management team is a grassroots organization devoted to community policing, home-buyer assistance, and beautification in the Dwight Street area of New Haven. Shanklin describes the first meetings of the organization in a storefront on the corner of Day and Chapel Streets. She also describes the yearly festival organized by the Management Team. After a number of years of successful Management Team activity, the members formed a sister organization, the Greater Dwight Development Corporation. The centralization allowed for easier access to funds and political power without blunting the grassroots, community-centered nature of the organization. Shanklin explains the membership structures of the Management Team, and describes its relationships with Yale and St. Rafael's hospital. She also touches on the slight resentment that some Dwight residents seem to feel about the activities and leadership of the Management Team.
    Length (min): 56
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Sharnik, Barbara, 2007 February 24; computer file (WAV)
    Barbara Sharnick describes her childhood interactions with her mother and grandparents, drawing upon the role of her congressionalist faith on her childhood and concept of family. She speaks from a New Haven nursing home. She illustrates a typical day there, in which she often has most of the day free to reflect, write short stories, and spend time with other residents. She shares anecdotes about marriage and sacrifice, family and obligations, and her relationships with other residents. She talks about aspects of the nursing home that enhance and detract from her vision of a home. She compares her relaxed, reflective time as a nursing home resident with her active experiences as a young woman studying journalism, working in government and advertising, traveling around the country and parts of Europe, and raising a family with her late husband, John. She describes shifts she's noticed throughout her lifetime in social relations, including interactions between the young and old and those between children and their parents. She draws upon her past and current experiences and those of others in her reflections. She talks about her visions of an ideal nursing home, a group home of several elderly residents with home medical care and an active living arrangement in which they could help each other by paying bills and cooking together, among other things.
    Interviewer: Serrano, Jose
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Silverman, Robert, 2004 May 6; computer file (WAV)
    Robert Silverman's family moved to New Haven in the mid-1930s and to the Legion Avenue neighborhood in 1939, where they became a part of the local Jewish community. He grew up and lived there until 1954, when Richard Lee's redevelopment projects forced residents and businesses out. Silverman talks about the many small businesses that he patronized in the neighborhood, including local grocery stores and various bakeries including Lenders' bagels. Although the area was largely Jewish, he talks about the ethnic diversity there and the lack of significant tension. He also discusses the nearby Oak Street area, which he characterizes as composed largely of African American families and poorer Italian and Jewish families. Silverman then discusses the redevelopment projects of the 1950s under Mayor Richard Lee and New Haven's designation as a Model City by the federal government. While everyone in his neighborhood was initially excited at the renewal proposals and the money they promised to bring in, they soon turned against the project when they realized the extent of the demolition plans. As homeowners and businesses were displaced, Silverman remembers, they lodged complaints against the Lee administration but to no avail. He laments the tragic loss of community and the local business establishments as a great tragedy of the redevelopment schemes.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Simmons, Mary Jane, 2006 April 18; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Ong, Donna
  - Slie, Rev. Samuel, 2005 April 27; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: James, Jennifer; Beyersdorf, Mark; and Bettwy, Bix
    Length (min): 80, 73
  - Slie, Sam, 2005 March 1; computer file (WAV)
    Sam Slie was born in 1925 and grew up in the Oak Street neighborhood of New Haven. He discusses his experiences as an African American in New Haven during the Great Depression and in the southern United States during World War II. Slie describes the Oak Street neighborhood as very ethnically diverse. He had Jewish and African American friends and talks about the variety of small businesses that Jews and African Americans owned. He did not personally feel much racial tension growing up. Slie talks about the economic difficulties of the Great Depression. He then talks about the high school tracking system in New Haven, in which academically motivated students attended Hillhouse High School while others attended Commercial High School or Boardman Trade School for training in manual labor careers. Slie attended Hillhouse High School and admits that he was intelligent but somewhat unmotivated as a student. His first real wakeup call to institutionalized racial discrimination occurred when a Marine recruiter came to Hillhouse during his senior year and informed him that he was ineligible to join the Marines because he was African American. After graduating, Slie was drafted and set to Fort Benning Georgia for training. As the only African American soldier in his regiment, Slie faced significant discrimination and the reality of Jim Crow segregation when he arrived in the South. He recounts his experiences with the color line in North Carolina and Georgia and his growing awareness of racial prejudice during his early adulthood.
  - Soto, Mercedes, 2007 March 2; computer file (WAV)
    Mercedes Soto, who grew up in Gary, Indiana, describes her involvement in LEAP since 1995. LEAP, Leadership, Education, and Athletics in Partnership, is a New Haven youth mentoring program that began 1992. She discusses her experiences working with displaced and unmotivated New Haven youth in both after-school and summer programs. She describes the visions, challenges, and rewards of interacting with and empowering young people. She talks about the skills she believes LEAP creates and enhances in New Haven youth, including those in leadership development and tolerance. She explains why she believes the experiential learning encouraged by LEAP is fundamental not only to an academic curriculum, but also to the development of the self. She talks about the relationship of LEAP and school systems, detailing the problems the organization has faced over the years. She describes the spread of LEAP into other surrounding cities, such as Hartford and Bridgeport. She talks about the challenges and rewards of continuing and expanding upon the strengths of the New Haven chapter. She shares anecdotes of people, events, and situations that she believes illustrate LEAP's role in enhancing relationships among and within youth, their families, teachers, administrators, and the community.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Spodick, Peter, 2006 April 8; computer file (WAV)
    Peter Spodick was born in New Haven, and attended Yale College and Yale Law School. He grew up in Woodbridge, but spent a great deal of time in New Haven as child. He describes his childhood as an age of innocence. Although he was part of small Jewish minority in Woodbridge, Spodick felt no discomfort on this count. He remembers walking the streets of downtown New Haven at night, with no sense of fear. But now, Spodick suggests, things have changed. Spodick describes the changing role of Yale in the New Haven community, the shifting landscape of downtown New Haven, and the failure of personal relationships in the city. Spodick's father worked in New York City movie theaters during the silent film era, so Spodick's move to the film industry came as little surprise. Spodick discusses his career in the movie theater business, including run-ins with the Walk Disney Company and with Steven Spielberg. Spodick also discusses the old Lincoln Theater in New Haven, which specialized in foreign and artistic films, and recalls the days when New Haven had a number of small movie theaters. York Square Cinema, which closed in 2005, was the last of its kind.
    Interviewer: Levine, Mimi
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Stitzer, Nancy, 2005 March 15; computer file (WAV)
    Nancy Stitzer, a white student, was part of the first generation of students who were bussed to Bassett Junior High School. She also Hillhouse High School during the 1967 race riot there. Stitzer remembers the bussing and integration experience very negatively and believes that it hurt the cohesion of her school class. She explains that many students went to private schools if their parents could afford it, while those who could not faced bussing and redistricting that broke up their classes and friendships. Because of bussing, Stitzer explained, she could not participate in afterschool activities at Bassett. She considers those who made it through the bussing years to be "survivors." Stitzer also talks about the 1967 race riot at Hillhouse High School and remembers being very frightened of the violence. She is surprised to learn that the riot started internally, for she remembers Black Panthers starting the riot. She is also surprised to learn about the police presence after the riot, brought on at the behest of many of the older teachers at the school.
    Length (min): 17, 13
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Teitelman, Sam, 2005 February 16; computer file (WAV)
    Samuel Teitelman, a first-generation Russian immigrant, was born in Cuba and came to New Haven with his parents in the 1920s after living shortly in New York City. He describes living in the Oak Street-Legion Avenue neighborhoodand recalls visiting the small businesses owned by people from a variety of backgrounds, including Jewish, Italian, and Polish. He discusses the familiarity among neighbors from a variety of countries and cultures, the different degrees of their assimilation to the American language and culture, and their varied connections to their immigrant homelands. He talks about the growth of ethnic enclaves as immigrants moved to different New Haven neighborhoods with the new settlement of other minority and immigrant groups. As a child, he spoke Yiddish at home, but he says that outside of the home, he mainly spoke English, both with his Jewish and non-Jewish peers. He talks about the centrality of the Jewish culture in his upbringing. He describes his childhood as predominately spent going to his synagogue's services and activities, which he describes as a social and educational outlet for his family. A soldier in WWII, he describes his later adjustment to civilian life, sharing changes he noticed in his childhood neighborhood's population and establishments. Now active at his childhood synagogue, he discusses his visions for its future, weighing the costs and benefits of preserving and renovating its facilities.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Tenzer, Virginia, 2007 March 29; computer file (WAV)
    Virginia Tenzer was born in Watertown, CT, the 11th of 12 children of Italian immigrant parents. After graduating UConn, she married a Yale graduate student, and moved to New Haven in the early 1950s. Tenzer's husband's work moved them around a lot, but the couple returned to New Haven upon his retirement in 1994, buying a co-op in the University Towers. Tenzer describes the peculiar co-operative structure of her building, which led to a protacted legal battle with a group of developers in the late 1990s. These legal issues depleted much of the cooperative's money, forcing the Towers to declare bankruptcy. Tenzer talks about her neighbors, the building's management, and social life in the building.
    Interviewer: Ammon, Francesca
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Trachten, Murray, 2005 March 30; computer file (WAV)
    Murray Trachten, born in Arizona, moved to New Haven as a young child. He describes his multicultural Greenwood Street neighborhood in a devout Jewish household among extended Russian family members. He describes his neighborhood as lower middle-class and his neighbors as ethnically diverse, including people of Jewish, Italian, and African-American descent. He says that his family's social life centered on the local Hebrew school, The New Haven Hebrew School, and their local synagogue, Orchard Street Synagogue. He shares examples of times he was aware of and sometimes uncomfortable with his difference as a Jewish student in his encounters with non-Jewish students. He remembers having mixed feelings about this difference. He says that he enjoyed the sense of security of being with his family but did not enjoy not being able to interact with other children, especially on Sabbath days. He talks about learning English in school while remaining fluent in Yiddish and his family's stress on education. He describes how his notion of cultural difference changed during his college years at NYU and later years in law school, where he was exposed to cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. He talks about the role of his Jewish faith and upbringing in how he has raised his family. He discusses changes he has noticed in his childhood neighborhood, particularly after effect of 1950s and 60s urban renewal policies on Jewish businesses.
    Length (min): 52
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Tucker, Adeline, 2004 November 19; computer file (WAV)